hello guys welcome to my video about the
Transformer and this is actually the
person 2.0 of my series on the
Transformer I had a previous video in
which I talked about the Transformer but
the audio quality was not good and as
suggested by my viewers as the video was
really uh had a huge success the viewers
suggested me to to improve their audio
quality so this this is why I'm doing
this video
uh you don't have to watch the previous
series because I would be doing
basically the same things but with some
improvements so I'm actually
compensating from some mistakes I made
or from some improvements that I could
add
after watching this video I suggest
watch my watching my other video about
or how to code a Transformer model from
scratch so how to code the model itself
how to train it online data and how to
inference it stick it with me because
it's gonna be a little long journey but
for sure what
now before we talk about the Transformer
I want to first talk about recurrent
neural networks so the networks that
were used before they introduced the
transformer for most of the sequence to
sequence jobs tasks so let's review them
recurring neural networks existed a long
time before the Transformer and they
allowed to map one sequence of input to
another sequence of output in this case
our input is X and we want an input
sequence Y what we did before is that we
split the sequence into single items so
we gave the recurrent neural network the
first item as input so X1 along with an
initial State usually made up of only
zeros and the recurrent normal Network
produced an output let's call it y1
and this happened at the first time step
then we took the hidden State this is
called the hidden state of the network
of the previous time step along with the
next input token so X2 and the network
had to produce the SEC the second output
token Y2 and then we did it the same
procedure at the third time step in
which we took the hidden state of the
previous time step along with the input
State the input token at the time steps
3 and the network has to produce the
next output token which is Y3 if you
have enter n tokens you need n time
steps to map a end sequence input into
an end sequence output
this worked fine for a lot of tasks but
had some problems let's review them
the problems with recurring neural
networks first of all are that they are
slow for long sequences because think of
the process we did before we have kind
of like a for Loop in which we do the
same operation for every token in the
input so if you have the longer the
sequence the longer this computation and
this made the the network not easy to
train for long sequences the second
problem was the vanishing or the
exploding gradients now you may have
heard these terms or expression on the
Internet or from other videos but I will
try to give you a brief Insight on what
does what do they mean on a practical
level so as you know
Frameworks like Pi torch they convert
our networks into a computation graph so
basically suppose we have a computation
graph I this is not an error network I
will making I will be making a
computational graph that is very simple
has nothing to do with the neural
networks but will show you the problems
that we have so imagine we have two
inputs X and another input let's call it
y
our computational graph first let's say
multiplies these two numbers so we have
a first a function let's call it f of x
and y
that is X multiplied by y
let me multiplied and the result let's
call it Z
is map is given to another function
let's call this function G of Z is equal
to let's say Z squared
what our phytorch for example does it's
that pytorch want to calculate the
usually we have a loss function by torch
calculates the derivative of the loss
function with respects to its each
weight in this case we just calculate
the derivative of the G function so the
output function with respect to all of
its inputs so derivative of G
with respect to X let's say is equal to
the derivative of G with respect to f
and multiplied by the derivative of f
with respect to X
these two should kind of cancel out this
is called the chain Rule now as you can
see
the longer the chain of computation so
if we have many nodes one after another
the longer this multiplication chain so
here we have two because the distance
from this node and this is two but
imagine you have 100 or 1000
now imagine this number is 0.5 and this
number is 0.5 also the resulting numbers
when multiplied together is a number
that is smaller than the two initial
numbers it's gone up 0.25 because it's
one to one half multiplied by one half
is one fourth
so if we have two numbers that are
smaller than one and we multiply them
together they will produce an even
smaller number and if we have two
numbers that are bigger than one and we
multiply them together they will produce
a number that is bigger than both of
them so if we have a very long chain of
computation it eventually will either
become a very big number or a very small
number
and this is not desirable first of all
because our CPU of our GPU can only
represent numbers up to a certain
Precision let's say 32-bit or 64-bit and
if the number becomes too small the
contribution of this number to the
output will become very small so when
the pi torch or our automatic let's say
our framework will calculate how to
adjust the weights the weight will move
very very very slowly because the
contribution of this product is will be
a very small number
and this means that we have the gradient
is Vanishing or in the other case it can
explode become very big numbers
and this is a problem the next problem
is difficulty in accessing information
from long time ago
what does it mean it means that as you
remember from the previous slide we saw
that the first input token is given to
the recurrent neural network to with
along with the first state
now we need to think that the recurrent
neural network is a long graph of
computation it will produce a new hidden
State then we will use the the new
hidden State along with the next token
to produce the next output if we have a
very long sequence
um of input sequence the last token will
have a hidden state whose contribution
from the first token has nearly gone
because of this long chain of
multiplication so actually the last
token will not depend much on the first
token and this is also not good because
for example we know as humans that in a
text in a quite long text the context
that we saw let's say 200 words before
still relevant to the context of the
current words and this is something that
the RNN could not map
and this is why we have the Transformer
so the Transformer solves these problems
with the recurrent neural networks and
we will see how
the structure of the Transformer we can
divide into two macro blocks the first
macro block is called encoder and it's
this part here
the second macro block is called a
decoder and it's the second part here
the third part here you see on the top
it's just a linear layer and we will see
why it's there and what it is function
so and the two layers so the encoder and
the decoder are connected by this
connection you can see here
in which some output of the encoder is
sent as input to the decoder and we will
also see how let's start first of all
with some notations that I will be using
during my explanation and you should be
familiar with this notation also to
review some maths so the first thing we
should be familiar with is matrix
multiplication so imagine we have a
input Matrix
which is a sequence of let's say words
so sequence by D model and we will see
why it's called sequence by the model so
imagine we have a matrix that is a 6 by
512 in which each row is a word
and this word is not made of characters
but by 512 numbers so each word is
represented by
512 numbers okay like this imagine you
have 512 of them along this row 512
along this other row etc etc one two
three four five so we need another one
here okay the first word we will call it
a the second B the C D E and F
if we multiply this matrix by another
Matrix let's say the transpose of this
Matrix so it's a matrix where the rows
becomes columns
so three
four
five and
six
this word will be here B C D E and F and
then we have
um
512 numbers along each column because
before we had them on the rows now they
will become on the column so here we
have the 512 number
etc etc
this is a matrix that is
512 by 6 so let me add some brackets
here if we multiply them we will get a
new Matrix that is we cancel the inner
dimensions and we get the outer
Dimension so it will become six by six
so it will be 6 rows by 6 rows so let's
draw it
how do we calculate the values of this
output Matrix this is six by six
this is the dot product of the first row
with the First Column so this is a
multiplied by a this the second value is
the first row with the second column the
third value is the first row with the
third column
until the last column so a multiplied by
F Etc what is the dot product is
basically you take the first number of
the first row so here we have 512
numbers here we have 512 numbers so you
take the first number of the first row
and the first number of the First Column
you multiply them together
second value of the first row second
value of the First Column you multiply
them together and then you add all these
numbers together so it will be let's say
uh this number multiplied by this plus
this number multiplied by this plus this
number multiplied by this plus this
number multiplied by this plus you sum
all this number together and this is the
a DOT product a so we should be familiar
with this notation because I will be
using it a lot in the next slides let's
start our journey with of the
Transformer uh by looking at the encoder
so the encoder
starts with the input embeddings so what
is an input embedding
first of all let's start with our
sentence we have a sentence of in this
case six words what we do is we tokenize
it we transform the sentence into tokens
what does it mean to tokenize we split
them into single words
it is not necessary to always split the
sentence using single words we can even
split the sentence in part in smaller
parts that are even smaller than a
single word so we could even split this
a sentence into let's say 20 tokens by
using the each by splitting each word
into multiple words this is usually done
in most modern
Transformer models but we will not be
doing it otherwise it's really difficult
to visualize so let's suppose we have
this input sentence and we split into
tokens and each token is a single word
the next step we do is we map these
words into numbers
and these numbers represent the position
of these words in our vocabulary so
imagine we have a vocabulary of all the
possible words that appear in our
training set each word will occupy a
position in this vocabulary so for
example the word will occupy the
position 105 the word the cat will
occupy the position 6500
Etc
and as you can see this cat here has the
same number as this cat here because
they occupy the same position in the
vocabulary
we take these numbers which are called
input IDs and we map them into a vector
of size 512.
this Vector is a vector made of 512
numbers
and we always map the same word to
always the same embedding
however this number is not fixed it's a
parameter for our model so our model
will learn to change these numbers in
such a way that it represents the
meaning of the word so the input ID is
never change because our vocabulary is
fixed but the embedding will change
along with the training process of the
model so the embeddings numbers will
change according to the needs of the
loss function so the input embedding are
basically mapping our single word into
an embedding of size 512 and we call
this quantity 512 D model because it's
the same name that it's also used in the
paper attention is all you need
let's look at the next layer of the
encoder which is the positional encoding
so what is positional encoding
what we want is that each word should
carry some information about its
position in the sentence because now we
built a matrix of words that are
embeddings but they don't convey any
information about how where that
particular word is inside the sentence
and this is the job of the positional
encoding so what we do
we want the model to treat words that
appear close to each other as close and
words that are distant as distant so we
want the model to see this information
about the special information that we
see with our eyes so for example when we
see this sentence what is positional
encoding we know that the word what is
more far from the word
um is compared to encoding because we we
have this partial information given by
our eyes but the model cannot see this
so we need to give some information to
the model about how the words are
specially distributed inside of the
sentence
and we want the positional encoding to
represent a pattern that the model can
learn and we will see how
imagine we have our original sentence
your cat is a lovely cat what we do is
we first convert into embeddings using
the previous layer so the input
embeddings and these are embeddings of
size 512 then we create some special
vectors called the positional encoding
vectors that we add to these embeddings
so this Vector we see here in red
is a vector of size 512 which is not
learned it's computed once and not
learned along with the training process
it's fixed and this word this Vector
represents the position of the word
inside of the sentence
and this should give us a output that is
a vector of size again 512 because we
are summing this number with this number
this number with this number so the
First Dimension with the First Dimension
the second dimension with that so we
will get a new Vector of the same size
of the input vectors or how are these
position in both embedding calculated
let's see
imagine we have a smaller sentence let's
say your cat is and you may have seen
the following expressions from the paper
what we do is we create a vector of five
of size D model so 512 and for each
position in this Vector we calculate the
value using these two expressions
using these arguments so the first
argument indicates the position of the
word inside of the sentence so the word
your occupies the position zero and we
use them for the even Dimension so the
zero the two the four the 510 Etc we use
the first expression so the sine and for
the other positions of this Vector we
use the second expression
and we do this for all the words inside
of the sentence so this particular
embedding is calculated p e of 1 0
because it's the first word embedding
zero so this one represents the argument
pause and this 0 represents the argument
2 I and p e of 1 1 means that the first
word uh Dimension one so we will use the
cosine
giving the position one and the two I
will be equal to 2i plus 1 will be equal
to 1.
and we do this for this third word Etc
if we have another sentence we will not
have different positional encodings
we will have the same vectors even for
different sentences because the
positional encoding are computed once
and reused for every sentence that our
model will see
during inference or training so we only
compute the positional encoding once
when we create the model we save them
and then we reuse them we don't need to
compute it every time we feed the feed a
sentence to the model
so why the authors chose the cosine and
the sine functions to represent
positional encodings because let's watch
the plot of these two functions uh the
you can see the plot is by position so
the position of the word inside of the
sentence and this depth is the dimension
along the vector so the two I that you
see saw before in the previous
expressions
and if we plot them we can see as humans
a pattern here and we hope that the
model can also see this path okay the
next layer of the encoder is the
multi-head attention
we will not go inside of the multi-head
attention first we will first visualize
the single head attention so the
self-attention with a single head and
let's do it
so what is self-attention self attention
is a mechanism that existed before they
introduced the Transformer the Alters of
the Transformer just changed it into a
multi-head attention so how did the
self-attention work
the self-attention allows the model to
relate words to each other
okay so we had the input embeddings that
capture the meaning of the word then we
have the positional encoding that give
the information about the position of
the word inside of the sentence now we
want this self-attention to relate words
to each other
now imagine we have uh in an input
sequence of six word with the D model of
size 512.
which can be represented as a matrix
that we will call Q K and V so our q k
and V is a same Matrix are the same
Matrix representing the input so the
input of six words with the dimension of
512 so each word is represented by a
vector of size 512. we basically apply
this formula we saw here from the paper
to calculate the attention the self
attention in this case why
self-attention because it's the each
word in the sentence related to other
words in the same sentence so it's
self-attention
so we start with our Q Matrix which is
uh the input sentence so let's visualize
it for example so we have six rows and
on this uh on the columns we have 512
column now they are really difficult to
draw but let's say we have 512 columns
and here we have six okay now what we do
according to this formula we multiply it
by the same sentence but transposed so
the transpose of the K which is again
the same input sequence
we divide it by the square root of 512
and then we apply this soft Max
the output of this as we saw before in
in the initial Matrix and notations we
saw that when we multiply 6 by 512 with
another Matrix that is 512 by 6 we
obtain a new Matrix that is six by six
and each value in this Matrix represents
the dot product of the first row with
the First Column this represents the dot
product of the first row with the second
column Etc
the values here are actually randomly
generated so don't concentrate on the
values what you should notice is that
the soft Max makes all these values in
such a way that they sum up to one so
this Row for example here some sums up
to one this other row also sums up to
one etc etc and this value we see here
it's the dot product of the first word
with the embedding of the word itself
this value here is the dot product of
the embedding of the word your with the
embedding of the word cat and this value
here is the dot product of the word the
embedding of the word your with the
embedding of the word is
the next thing we and this value
represents somehow a score that how
intense is the relationship between one
word and another let's go uh ahead with
the formula so for now we just
multiplied Q by K divided by the square
root of Decay applied to the soft Max
but we didn't multiply by V
so let's go forward we multiply this
matrix by V and we obtain a new Matrix
which is 6 by 512 so if we multiply a
matrix that is 6 by 6 with another that
is 6 by 512 we get a new Matrix that is
6 by 512 and one thing you should notice
is that with the dimension of this
Matrix is exactly the dimension of the
initial Matrix from which we started
this what does it mean that we obtain a
new Matrix that is six rows so let's say
six rows
with 512 columns
in which each these are our words so we
have six words and each word has an
embedding of Dimension 512 so now this
embedding here represents not only the
meaning of the word which was given by
the input embedding not only the
position of the word which was added by
the positional encoding but now somehow
this special embedding so these values
represent a special embedding that also
captures the relationship of this
particular word with all the other words
and this particular embedding of this
word here also captures not only its
meaning not only its position inside of
the sentence but also the relationship
of this word with all the other words
I want to remind you that this is not
the multi-head attention we are just
watching the self-attention so one head
we will we will see later how this
becomes the multi-head attention
self-attention has some properties that
are very desirable
first of all it's permutation invariant
what does it mean to be permutation
invariant it means that if we have a
matrix let's say
first we had a matrix of six words in
this case the let's say just four words
so a b c and d
and suppose by applying the formula
before this produces this particular
Matrix in which the there is new special
embedding
for the word a a new special embedding
for the word b a new special bedding for
the word c and d so let's call it a
prime B Prime C Prime D Prime if we
change the position of these two rows
the values will not change the position
of the output will change accordingly so
the values of B Prime will not change it
will just change in the the position and
also the C will also change position but
the values in each Vector will not
change and this is a desirable
properties self-attention as of now
requires no parameters I mean I didn't
introduce any parameter that is learned
by the model I just took the initial
sentence of in this case six words
we multiplied it by itself we divide it
by a fixed quantity which is the square
root of 512 and then we apply the soft
Max which is not introducing any
parameters so for now the self-attention
rate didn't require any parameter except
for the embedding of the words
this will change later when we introduce
the multi-head attention
also we expect because the each value in
the self-attention in the soft Max
Matrix is a DOT product of the word
embedding with itself and the other
words we expect the values along the
diagonal to be the maximum because it's
the dot product dot product of each word
with itself
and
there is another property of this Matrix
that is before we apply the soft softmax
if we replace the value in this Matrix
suppose we don't want the word your and
Cat to interact with each other or we
don't want the word let's say is and the
lovely to interact with each other what
we can do is before we apply the softmax
we can replace this value with minus
infinity and also this value with minus
infinity
and when we apply the soft Max the soft
Max will replace minus infinity with 0.
because as you remember the soft Max is
e to the power of x if x is going to
minus infinity e will be e to the power
of minus infinity will become very very
close to zero so basically zero
this is a desirable property that we
will use in the decoder of the
Transformer now let's have a look at
what is a multi-head attention so what
we just saw was the self attention and
we want to convert it into a
multi-headed tension you may have seen
these expressions from the paper but
don't worry I will explain them one by
one so let's go
imagine we have our encoder so we are on
the encoder side of of the Transformer
and we have our input sentence which is
let's say 6 by 512 so Six Word by 512 is
the size of the embedding of each word
in this case I call it sequence by D
model so sequence is the sequence length
as you can see on the legend in the
bottom left of the slide and the D model
is the size of the embedding Vector
which is 512. what we do just like the
picture shows
and we take this input and we make four
copies of it one will be sent uh wait
one will be sent along this connection
we can see here and three will be sent
to the multi-header attention with three
respective names so it's the same input
that becomes three matrices that are
equal to input one is called the query
one is called key and one is called
value so basically we are taking this
input and making three copies of it one
we call Q K and B they have of course
the same dimension
what does the multihead attention do
first of all it multiplies these three
matrices by three parameter matrices
called WQ w k and WV
these matrices have Dimension D model by
D model so if we multiply a matrix that
is sequence by the model with another
one that is D model by D model we get a
new Matrix as output that is sequenced
by D model so basically the same
Dimension as the starting Matrix
and we will call them Q Prime K Prime
and V Prime
our next step is to split these matrices
into smaller matrices let's see how
we can split this Matrix Q Prime by the
sequence Dimension or by the D model
dimension
in the multi-hat attention we always
split by the D model Dimension so every
head will see the full sentence but a
smaller part of the embedding of each
word
so if we have an embedding of let's say
512 it will become smaller embeddings of
512 divided by four and we call this
quantity d k so d k is D model divided
by H where H is the number of heads in
our case we have H equal to 4.
we can calculate the attention between
these smaller matrices so q1 K1 and V1
using the expression taken from the
paper
and this will result into a small Matrix
called Head 1 head 2 head 3 and head
four the dimension of head 1 up to head
four is sequence by d v
what is DV is basically it's equal to DK
it's just called a DV because the last
multiplication is done by V and in the
paper they call it DV so I am also
sticking to the same names
our next step is to multi combine these
matrices these small heads
by concatenating them along the DV
Dimension just like the paper says so we
can cut all this head together and we
get a new Matrix that is sequence by H
multiplied by DV
where H multiplied by DV as we know DV
is equal to d k so H multiplied by DV is
equal to D model so we get back the
initial shape so it's sequence by D
model here
the next step is to multiply the result
of this concatenation by w o
and W O is a matrix that is H multiplied
by DV so D model multiple with the other
dimension being T model and the result
of this is a new Matrix that is the
result of the multi-head attention which
is sequenced by D model
so the multi had attention instead of
calculating the attention between these
matrices here so Q Prime K Prime and V
Prime splits them along the D model
Dimension into smaller matrices and
calculates the attention between these
smaller matrices so each head is
watching the full sentence but as
different aspect of the embedding of
each word why we want this because we
want the each head to watch different
aspects of the same word for example in
the Chinese language but also in other
languages one word may be a noun in some
cases maybe a verb in some other cases
maybe a adverb in some other cases
depending on the context
so what we want is that one head maybe
learns to relate that word as a noun
another head maybe learns to relate that
word as a verb and another head learn to
release that verb as an objective or
adverb
so this is why we want a multi-head
attention
now you may also have seen online that
the the attention can be visualized and
I will show you how when we calculate
the attention between the Q and the K
matrices so when we do this operation so
the soft Max of Q multiplied by the K
divided by the square root of d k
we get a new Matrix just like we saw
before which is sequenced by sequence
and this represents a score that
represents the intensity of the
relationship between the two words
we can visualize this
and this will produce a visualization uh
similar to this one which I took from
the paper in which we see how the all
the heads work so for example if we
concentrate on this work making this
word here we can see that making is
related to the word difficult so this
word here by different heads so the blue
head the red head and the green head
but the wire let's say the Violet head
is not relating this two word together
so making and difficult is not related
by the violet or the pink head
The Violet head or the pink head they
are relating the word making to other
words for example to this word 2009
why this is the case because maybe this
pink head could see the part of the
embedding that these other heads could
not see that made this interaction
possible between these two words
you may be also wondering why these
three mattresses are called query keys
and values
okay the terms come from the database
terminology or from the python-like
dictionaries but I would also like to
give my interpretation of my own making
a very simple example I think it's quite
easy to
um
understand
so imagine we have a python-like
dictionary or a database in which we
have keys and values
the keys are the category of movies and
the values are the movies belonging to
that category in my case I just put one
value
so we have Romantics category which
includes Titanic we have action movies
that include the Dark Knight Etc imagine
we also have a user that makes a query
and the query is love
because we are in the Transformer world
all these words actually are represented
by embeddings of size 512.
so what our Transformer will do he will
convert this word love into an embedding
of 512 all these queries and values are
already embeddings of 512 and it will
calculate the dot product between the
query and all the keys
just like the formula so as you remember
the formula is a soft Max of query
multiplied by the transpose of the keys
divided by the square root of the model
so we are doing the dot product of all
the queries with all the keys
in this case the word love with all the
keys one by one
and this will result in a score that
will amplify some values or not amplify
other values
um in this case our embedding may be in
such a way that the word love and
romantic are inter are related to each
other the word love and comedy are also
related to each other but not so
intensively like the word love and
romantic so it's more how to say let's
less strong relationship but maybe the
word horror and love are not related at
all so maybe their soft Max score is
very close to zero
our next
um
layer in the encoder is the ADD and norm
and to introduce the other Norm we need
the layer normalization so let's see
what is the layer normalization
layer normalization is a layer that okay
let's make a practical example imagine
we have a batch of n items in this case
n is equal to three
item one item two item three each of
these items will have some features it
could be an embedding so for example it
could be a feature of a vector of size
512 but it could be a very big Matrix of
thousands of features doesn't matter
what we do is we calculate the mean and
the variance of each of these items
independently from each other
and we replace each value with another
value that is given by this expression
so basically we are normalizing so that
the new values are all in the range 0 to
1.
actually we also multiply this new value
with a parameter called gamma and then
we add another parameter called beta and
this gamma and beta are learnable
parameters
and the model should learn to multiply
and add these parameters so as to
amplify the value that it wants to be
Amplified and not amplify that value
that it doesn't want to be Amplified
uh so we don't just normalize we
actually introduce some parameters
and I found a really nice visualization
from papers with code.com
in which we see the difference between
batch norm and layer Norm so as we can
see in the layer normalization we are
calculating if n is the batch Dimension
we are calculating all the values
belonging to one item in the batch
while in the batch Norm we are
calculating the same feature for all the
batch so for all the items in the batch
so we are mixing let's say values from
different items of the batch while in
the layer normalization we are treating
each item in the batch independently
which will have its own mean and its own
variance
let's look at the decoder now
um in the encoder we saw the input
embeddings in this call in this case
they are called output embeddings but
the underlying working is the same here
also we have the positional encoding and
they are also the same as the Imp as the
encoder
the next layer is the musket multi-head
attention and we will see it now we also
have the multi-head attention here with
the
here we should see that the
there is the encoder here that produces
the output and is sent to the decoder in
the forms of keys
and values
while the query so this connection here
is the query coming from the decoder
so in this multi-head attention it's not
a self-attention anymore it's a cross
attention because we are taking two
sentences one is sent from the encoder
side so let's write encoder in which we
provide the output of the encoder and we
use it as a query as keys and values
while the output of the masked
multi-head attention is used as the
query in this multi-head attention
and the musket multi-head attention is
the self-attention of the input sentence
of the decoder so we take the input
sentence of the decoder we transform
into embeddings we add the depositional
encoding we give it to this multi-head
attention in which the query key and
values are the same input sequence we do
the ADD and Norm then we send this as
the queries of the multi-head attention
while the keys and the values are coming
from the encoder then we do the add the
norm
I will not be showing the feed forward
which is just a fully connected layer
we then send the output of the feed
forward to the ADD and norm and finally
to the linear layer which we will see
later so let's have a look at the Muscat
multi-head attention and how it differs
from a normal multi-head attention
what we want our goal is that we want to
make the model causal it means that the
output at a certain position can only
depend on the words on the previous
position so the model must not be able
to see future words how can we achieve
that
as you saw the the output of the soft
Max in the attention calculation formula
is this Matrix sequence by sequence if
we want to hide the interaction of some
words with other words we delete this
value and we replace it with minus
infinity before we apply the soft Max so
that the soft Max will replace this
value with 0. and we do this for all the
interaction that we don't want so we
don't want your to watch future words so
we don't want your to watch cat is a
lovely cat and we don't want the word
cat to watch future words but only all
the words that come before it or the
word itself so we don't want this this
this this also the same for the other
words Etc
so we can see that we are replacing all
the word all this values here that are
above this diagonal here so this is the
principal diagonal of the Matrix and we
want all the values that are above this
diagonal to be replaced with minus
infinity so that so that the soft Max
will replace them with zero let's see in
which stage of the multi-head attention
this mechanism is introduced so when we
calculate the attention between these
smaller matrices so q1 K1 and V1
before we apply this soft Max we replace
this values so this one this one this
one this one this one Etc with minus
infinity then we apply this soft Max and
then the soft Max will take care of
transforming these values into zeros so
basically we don't want these words to
interact with each other
and if we don't want this interaction
the model will learn to not make them
interact because the model will not get
any information from this interaction so
it's like this word cannot interact now
let's look at how the inference and
training works for a Transformer model
as I saw said previously we are dealing
with it we will be dealing with the
translation tasks so because it's easy
to visualize and it's easy to understand
all the steps let's start with the
training of the model we will go from an
English sentence I love you very much
into an Italian sentence it's a very
simple sentence it's easy to describe
let's go
we start with a description of the
of the Transformer model and we start
with our English sentence which is sent
to the encoder so our English sentence
here
on which we prepared and append to
special tokens one is called start of
sentence and one is called end of
sentence these two tokens are taken from
the vocabulary so they are special
tokens in our vocabulary that tells the
model what is the start position of a
sentence and what is the end of a
sentence we will see later why we need
them
for now just think that we take our
sentence we prepend a special token and
we append a special token
then what we do as you can see from the
picture we take our inputs we transform
into input embeddings we add the
positional encoding and then we send it
to the encoder
so this is our encoder input sequence by
the model we send it to the encoder it
will produce an output which is encode a
sequence by D model and it's called the
encoder output so as I saw we saw
previously the output of the encoder is
another Matrix that has the same
Dimension as the input Matrix
in which the embedding we can see it as
a sequence of embeddings in which this
embedding is special because it captures
not only the meaning of the word which
was given by the input embedding we saw
here so by this not only the position
which was given by the positional
encoding but also the interaction of
every word with every other word in the
same sentence because this is the
encoder so we are talking about
self-attention so it's the interaction
of each word in the sentence with all
the other words in the same sentence
we want to convert this sentence into
Italian so we prepare the input of the
decoder which is a start of sentence
as you can see from the picture of the
the Transformer the outputs here you can
see shifted right
what does it mean to shift right
basically it means we prepared a special
token called SOS start of sentence
you should also notice that these two
sequences actually they in when we code
the Transformer so if you watch my other
video on how to code a Transformer you
will see that we
make this sequence of fixed length so
that if we have a sentence that is te
amo multo or a very long sequence
actually when we feed them to the
Transformer they all becomes become of
the same length how to do this we add
padding words to reach the length the
desired length so if our model can
support let's say a sequence length of
1000 in this case we have a fourth
tokens we will add
996 tokens of padding to make this
sentence long enough to reach the
sequence length of course I'm not doing
it here because it's not easy to
visualize otherwise
okay we prepared this input for the
decoder we add transform into embeddings
we add the positional encoding then we
send it first to the multi-head
attentions to the musket
multi-haditation so along with the
causal mask
and then we take the output of the
encoder and we send it to the decoder as
keys and values while the queries are
coming from the musket so the queries
are coming from this layer and the keys
and the values are the output of the
encoder
this the output of all this block here
so all this big block here
will be a matrix that is sequence by the
model just like for the encoder
however we can see that this is still an
embedding because it's a D model it's a
vector of size 512 how can we relate
this
um embedding back into our dictionary
how can we understand what is this word
in our vocabulary that's why we need a
linear layer that will map sequence by D
model into another sequence by
vocabulary size so it will tell for
every embedding that it sees what is the
position of that word in our vocabulary
so that we can understand what is the
actual token that is output by the model
after that we apply the softmax and
then we have our label what we expect
the model to Output given this English
sentence
we expect the model to Output this te
amo multo end of sentence and this is
called the label or the target what we
do when we have the output of the model
and the corresponding label we calculate
the loss in this case is the cross
entropy loss and then we back propagate
the loss to all the weights
now let's understand why we have these
special tokens called SOS and EOS
basically you can see that here the
sequence length is 4 actually is 1000
because we have the padding but let's
say we don't have any padding so it's
four tokens start of sentence the ammo
multo and what we want is the T ammo
multo end of sentence so our model when
it will see the start of sentence token
it will output the first token as output
T when it will see T it will output ammo
when it will see armor it will output
molto and when it will see a multo it
will output end of sentence which will
indicate that okay the translation is
done
and we will see this mechanism in the
inference
ah this all happens in one time step
just like I promised at the beginning of
the video I said that with recurrental
or neural networks we have end time
steps to map n input sequence into an
output sequence but this problem would
be solved with the Transformer yes it
has been solved because you can see here
we didn't do any for Loop we just did
all in one pass we give an input
sequence to the encoder an input
sequence to the decoder we produced some
outputs we calculated that cross entropy
loss with the label and that's it it all
happens in one time step and this is the
power of the Transformer because it made
it very easy and very fast to train very
long sequences and with the very very
nice performance that you can see in
charge GPD you can see GPT in bird Etc
let's have a look at how inference works
again we have our English sentence I
love you very much we want to map it
into an Italian sentence
we have our usual Transformer we prepare
the input for the encoder which is start
of sentence I love you very much end of
sentence
we convert into input embeddings then we
add the positional encoding we prepare
the input for the encoder and we send it
to the encoder the encoder will produce
an output which is sequenced by the
model and we saw it before that it's a
sequence of special embeddings that
capture the meaning the position but
also the interaction of all the words
with other words
what we do is for the decoder we give
him just the start of sentence and of
course we keep the we add enough
embedding padding tokens to reach our
sequence length we just give the model
the start of sentence token and we again
we for this single token we convert into
embeddings we add the positional
encoding and we send it to the decoder
as decoder input the decoder will take
this
um his input as a query and the key and
the values coming from the encoder
and it will produce an output which is
sequenced by D model again we want the
linear layer to project it back to our
vocabulary and this projection is called
logits
what we do is we apply the soft Max
which will select given the logists will
give the position of the output word
will have the maximum score with the
soft Max this is how we know what words
to select from the vocabulary
and this hopefully should produce the
first output token which is T
if the model has been trained correctly
this however happens at time step one so
when we train the model Transformer
model it happens in one pass so we have
one input sequence one output sequence
we give it to the model we do it one
time step and the model will learn it
when we inference however we need to do
it token by token and we will also see
why this is the case
at time Step 2 we don't need to
recompute the encoder output again
because the over English sentence didn't
change so we hope the the encoder should
produce the same output for it and then
what we do is we take the output of the
previous sentence so
um
as T we append it to the input of the
decoder and then we feed it to the
decoder again with the output of the
encoder from the previous step
which will produce an output sequence
from the decoder side which we again
project back into our vocabulary and
we get the next token which is ammo
so as I saw before as I as I said before
we are not recalculating the output of
the encoder for every time step because
our English sentence didn't change at
all what is changing is the input of the
decoder because at every time step we
are appending the output of the previous
step to the input of the decoder we do
the same for the time step 3
and we do the same for the time step 4
and hopefully we will stop when we see
the end of sentence token because that
is that's how the model tells us to stop
inferencing
and this is how the inference works why
we needed four time steps
when we inference a model
um like the in this case the translation
model there are many strategies for
inferencing what we used is called
greedy strategy so for every step we get
the word with the maximum soft max value
and however this strategy Works uh
usually not bad but there are better
strategies
and one of them is called beam search
in beam search instead of always
greedily so this is that's why it's
called greedy instead of greedily taking
the maximum soft value we take the top B
values and then for each of these
choices we inference what are the next
possible tokens for each of the top B
values at every step and we keep only
the one with the B most probable
sequences and we delete the others this
is called beam search and it generally
it performs better
so thank you guys for watching uh I know
it was a long video but it was really
worth it to go through each aspect of
the Transformer I hope you enjoyed this
journey with me so please subscribe to
the channel and don't forget to watch my
other video on how to code a Transformer
model from scratch in which I describe
not only again the structure of the
Transformer model while coding it but I
also show you how to train it on a data
set of your choice how to inference it
and I also provided the code on GitHub
and the Ecolab notebook to train the
model directly on collab
please subscribe to the to the channel
and let me know what you didn't
understand so that I can give more
explanation and please tell me what are
the problems in this kind of videos or
in this particular video that I can
improve for the next videos thank you
very much and have a great rest of the
day